[With Spanish work permit]

Héctor Ramírez

Data Scientist | PhD in Physics

Brief résumé: I recently earned my PhD in Physics where I specialized in experimental data analysis and mathematical modeling. I led several short and long-term projects in collaboration with colleagues from several institutions in different countries. The results of which I have presented as a speaker in multiple international seminars and conferences. Moreover, I am continuously extending computer skills with numerous courses on Data Engineering, Data Science and Machine Learning. To mention some skills: Supervised and Unsupervised Learning with scikit-learn; Deep Learning with Keras, TensorFlow and PyTorch; NLP with NLTK and spaCy; SQL; PySpark, AWS; Tableau; etc.

Contact $(+34)693012381 \ \Box$ — Mail \square — LinkedIn $\boxed{\mathbf{n}}$ — GitHub \bigcirc — Webpage \bigcirc

Current residence Valencia, Spain. [Willing to relocate worldwide]

Birth and Nationality | May 20th, 1990 — Mexican.

Education

PhD in Physics | University of Valencia, Spain.

2015-2019 Dissertation: 'Noncanonical Approaches to Inflation'

MA in Advanced University of Valencia, Spain.

Physics 2013-2014 Dissertation: 'The Hu-Sawicki Model of Modified Gravity'

BA in Physics University of Veracruz, Mexico.

2008-2013 Dissertation: 'Quantum Chaos in the Dicke Model'

2012 University of Valencia (Academic exchange semester), Spain.

Additional training

I have been continuously learning **Data Engineering**, **Data Science** and **Machine Learning** techniques following the course plan by **DataCamp**, where I have completed more than 50 courses, some of which make up the following main tracks:

Data Scientist DataCamp - Certificate

2019 100-hour track on statistical and machine learning techniques to analyze and interpret complex data.

Data Analyst DataCamp - Certificate

2019 60-hour track on data visualization and manipulation techniques to uncover insights and help orga-

nizations make better decisions.

Machine Learning | DataCamp - Certificate

Fundamentals 2019 | 20-hour track on the fundamental concepts in Machine Learning.

Skills

Computer

Languages Python, SQL, Mathematica, Scala.

Data Engineering | PostgreSQL, Apache Airflow, Amazon Web Services (S3, SNS).

Data Analysis Spreadsheets, Tableau, NumPy, pandas.

Machine Learning scikit-learn, PySpark, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, XGBoost, NLTK, spaCy.

Visualization Matplotlib, Seaborn, Bokeh, Plotly.

Web HTML, CSS.

Other Git, Jupyter Notebook, Docker.

Soft skills

Communication Public speaking, persuasion, writing skills.

Leadership Project management, supervising, mentoring.

Critical Thinking Creativity, logical thinking, problem solving, research, organization.

Teamwork Collaboration, interpersonal skills, networking, social skills, team building.

Languages

Spanish: Native; English: Fluent; French: B2 level. I have also taken German and Italian courses.

Professional Experience

Acracy

Jan 2020 -

Technology Consultant

- Creation of SQL and NoSQL databases from scratch using AWS.
- Main software development using Python.

IFIC

of Walancia

 CSIC / U. of Valencia Jan 2015 - May 2019

- Researcher
- \bullet Fundamental research on primordial Cosmology.
- Data analyses, statistical and mathematical modeling using Python and Mathematica.
- Short- and long-term projects with international collaborators.

International projects

I have done research placements in the UK, Japan, Italy and in the Fermilab National Laboratory (USA), where I led short-and long-term collaborative projects and presented results as international speaker.

Apr - Jun, 2018	Institute of Cosmology and Gravitation (ICG), University of Portsmouth Portsmouth, UK.
Jan - Mar, 2018	Kavli Institute for the Physics and Mathematics of the Universe (IPMU), The University of Tokyo
May - Aug, 2017	Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab) & Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics – The University of Chicago
Apr - Jun, 2015	Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) Trieste, Italy.

Teaching

I have taught undergraduate courses managed by the Department of Theoretical Physics at the University of Valencia during four academic years—about 45 hours in the classroom (groups of around 15 students) + class preparation, per academic year.

Classical Mechanics	Teaching Assistant (2017-2019): Resolution of problems, examinations, evaluation of teaching contents and elaboration of teaching material.
Introductory Physics	Teaching Assistant (2015-2018): Resolution of problems, occasional lectures, examinations and grading.

Journal referee

I have referred scientific articles for the journals **Physical Review Letters** and **Physical Review D**, both from the American Physical Society (USA).

Awards and Fellowships

2015 - 2019	FPI Research fellow by the Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competitiveness (MINECO), Spanish Government.
$\mathrm{Jul} - \mathrm{Sep}, 2014$	Research scholarship granted by the University of Valencia
Jan - Jul, 2012	Grant for an abroad academic exchange semester by the University of Veracruz Carried out at the Faculty of Physics, <i>University of Valencia</i> .
2009 - 2011	Faculty award (x2) due to academic excellence University of Veracruz

Publications

Data Science

• "Your live Covid-19 tracker with Airflow and GitHub Pages", Towards Data Science; 2020.

Physics (scientific articles)

A total of 8 research articles published either in Physical Review D (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields — Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.568] (x5); Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields – Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.734] (x2); Physics of the Dark Universe (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.) [Impact factor: 5.4c25] (x1).

My full list of publications can be found in my Inspire page: http://inspirehep.net/author/profile/H.Ramirez.1

Talks

Conference talks

5 talks in Valencia, Paris, Teruel (Spain), Kyoto (Japan) and Portsmouth (UK).

Seminar talks

13 talks in Valencia (x2), Paris (x2), Tokyo, London, Portsmouth (UK), New York, Chicago, UC Berkeley (USA), Schladming (Austria) and Veracruz (Mexico).

Details about my talks can be found in https://hectoramirez.github.io/Files/CV/Talks.pdf .

Dr. Olga Mena Requejo

Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC/IFIC)

☑ — **②**

Prof. Nick E. Mavromatos

King's College London

- (

Prof. David Wands University of Portsmouth

 \blacksquare — \bigcirc

Prof. Shinji Tsujikawa Tokyo University of Science

- (